Preliminary Inventory to the Thomas Andrew Bailey and Paul B. Ryan collection, 1915-1979
Hoover Institution Archives
Thomas Andrew Bailey and Paul B. Ryan collection (Bailey-Ryan Collection),
1915-1979
75003
Hoover Institution Archives
17 manuscript boxes, 2 slide boxes, 13 microfilm reels, 1 phonotape (9 linear feet)
Correspondence, notes, photocopies of government documents, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the sinking of the Lusitania in 1915, and to the undeclared American-German naval war, 1939-1941. Collected by T. A. Bailey and Paul B. Ryan. Includes some papers of T. A. Bailey, relating especially to the Marshall Plan.
Bailey, Thomas Andrew, 1902-
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Scope And Contents Note
The collection contains research materials relating to the sinking of the British liner Lusitania by a German submarine on 7 May 1915. Included are copies of the records of the British official inquiry; the legal proceedings held by a U.S. Federal Court; letters from archival sources in Great Britain, Germany, Canada, and the United States; and a file of letters written in 1934 by Admiral Arno Spindler of the German Navy to Professor Thomas A. Bailey. Additional files contain correspondence with various professional and naval technical agencies, individual experts, and John Light, a professional diver who examined the wreck of the Lusitania off the coast of Ireland.
Lusitania (Steamship); Ryan, Paul B.; Economic assistance, American--Europe.; Europe.; Phonotapes.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Europe.; Slides (Photography).; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Neutrality.; World War, 1914-1918--Naval operations--Submarine.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Major ship overhead - Requirements (Box 1)
- Turner, Captain, biographical data
- Furbringer, Rear Admiral Werner (shipmate of Kept. Lieut. Schwieger of U-20), letter from
- Analysis of orders given to Captain Turner
- Analysis of witnesses and their affiliations
- Summary of 22 witnesses (statements sent in by U.S. Consul Wesley Frost)
- Biographical data on Lord Mersey, Sir Edward Carson, Sir Fredrick Smith
- Scott, Admiral Sir Percy, letter to The Times (London)
- Malone, Dudley Field, obituary and statement
- "The Great Lusitania Whitewash" by Paul B. Ryan, The American Neptune, January 1975
- New York, SS, Open Ash Port Sinking
- American Heritage, article purchased, not published as of, May 1975
- Book reviews - T. A. Bailey, published by American Historical Review
- The Stephens Letter (copy) - an example of how Simpson handles evidence
- Readers Digest condensed version of Simpson's book Lusitania
- Ellis book's charts and diagram and testimony regarding location of torpedo hit
- Judge Mayer and the Titanic law suit
- Herzog's review of Simpson's book in Marine Rundschau, 1973
- A partial tabulation of official British and German sources
- Great maritime disasters, Titanic, etc.
- New York Times
- Questions answered in Bailey-Ryan book
- New York Times index on Lusitania and news items
- The Times (London) news items
- World (New York) news items
- Von Muller, Admiral, diary
- British Cabinet and Parliament papers on Lusitania
- Parliamentary debates, May 10-11, 1915
- German archives and correspondence
- Spindler, Admiral Arno, La Guerre Sous-Marine, Volume II, cruise of U-20, U-27, U-28, U-30, May 1915 (Box 2)
- German Naval Records, Admiral Spindler, Der Handelskrieg mit U-Booten
- Foreign and German press analysis
- German Foreign Office information on Lusitania and Schwieger
- Royal Naval Reserved Merchant Cruisers (Brassey, 1914)
- American lives lost and U.S. ships sunk by U-boats, February 1, 1917
- Judge Mayer's opinion in Lusitania trial, New York City, 1918
- International law on visit and search
- Charts
- Charts used at Mersey Inquiry (compiled by Captain Turner)
- Mersey Hearings - Inquiry (open)
- Mersey Trial Proceedings in Camera
- Mersey Report (Verdict)
- List of Americans on board, Lusitania Claims, Senate Documents, 67th Congress, 2nd Session, No. 176
- Report on loss of S/S Falaba (Mersey)
- Location of ship sinkings in Queenstown area, May 5-7, 1915
- Instructions to British merchant captains, 1915
- Morton, Leslie, the look-out - a hero - decorated
- Admiralty chart used at Inquiry, Adm. 116/1416, C7943, of steamers Atlantic, May 5-7, 1915
- article in Journal of American Society of Naval Engineers, a reprint of British Engineering article, August 1907, November 1907
- Boiler explosions
- Schwieger, information on, from German sources and authors
- Plan view of 4 decks and hold of Lusitania
- Diagram of cargo storage on Lusitania (Mayer trial) (Box 3)
- Profile of Lusitania, L. Peskett testimony (Mayer trial), Quadruple Screw Turbine Ship
- Lusitania - Watertight compartmentation
- Diagram of compartmentation of Lusitania, Peskett testimony (Mayer trial)
- General correspondence with sources
- Warning messages sent to Lusitania
- British Naval Sea Patrol Officer, letter to Vice Admiral, Queenstown Patrol
- Lord, Walter, correspondence with
- The Goetz medal
- Schwieger's war-patrol diary
- Photographs (xerox copies) - Miscellaneous
- Diagrams of torpedo run and track of Lusitania, May 7, 1915
- Defense of the Realm Act
- Cartoons
- Photographs from U.S. Naval Historical Center, Washington, D.C.
- Photographs (xerox copies) from U.S. National Archives
- Engineering (British journal), illustrations, 1907
- The Blue Riband
- Copy of Lusitania's manifest (Box 4)
- May, Commander W. E., R.N., correspondence (research)
- British Public Record Office files
- Simpson's books, book reviews
- Simpson's books (U.S. and British) - Differences in the two editions
- Churchill, Winston, article on Lusitania, 1937
- Hoehling book Last Voyage of Lusitania, book reviews
- U.S. press opinion on Lusitania
- Analysis of boat drills, discipline of crew, life jackets, etc.
- Microfilm roll #197 (witnesses, etc.)
- Letters regarding London BBC broadcast on Lusitania
- Chronology
- The Zig-Zag issue
- U-boat characteristics
- Survivor from ship William P. Frye, sunk by U-boat
- Mayer Trial (New York Testimony), exhibits listed (Box 5)
- John Light's marked-up copy of Simpson's book (British version)
- Woodrow Wilson's note on Falaba to Lansing, June 2, 1915
- U.S. Naval Attaché, Berlin, reports to Washington (O.N.I.)
- U.S. Naval Historical Center, Washington, D.C. (xerox copies)
- Ships sunk by U-boats
- Cunard Company petition for limitation of liability
- Analysis of instruction to Captain Turner of Lusitania (Box 6)
- Correspondence - Miscellaneous
- Federal Records Center (New York City), letters
- Lusitania's Manifest - Correspondence
- Port collector - Correspondence
- Worley, Albert
- Mayer Trial Testimony II, pages 240-480
- Mayer Trial Testimony III, pages 481-717
- Mayer Trial Testimony IV, pages 718-960
- Wynne Hearings, Volume I, pages 6, 1-19 (Box 7)
- Wynne Hearings, Volume II, pages 197-403
- Proposed final decree by Cunard lawyers at Mayer Trial
- Value of Lusitania freight - Mayer Trial
- Interrogations and briefs (Cunard)
- Mayer Trial Testimony, pages 4a-239 (includes list of witnesses)
- Stephen's letter - Guns
- Canadian troops on board?
- Letter from U.S. Ambassador (Berlin) Dodd to T. A. Bailey, and page 2 of T. A. Bailey's letter, 1934
- Guns - Greenwich Naval Museum
- Spindler, Arno (German Admiral) (Box 8)
- Correspondence regarding Colin Simpson's book
- Letters in collecting evidence on Lusitania
- O'Connor, Daniel (NBC)
- Schwieger, Captain (of U-20)
- Woodrow Wilson and Mexican question
- Medal (Lusitania) by Goetz
- Humfrey Jordan book on Mauretania (sister ship of Lusitania)
- Professor Arthur Marder on Lusitania
- Plans of Lusitania (xerox copies)
- Walter Lord on Lord Mersey question
- Guns on board Lusitania
- Explosives, ammunition on board
- Bryan, W. J.
- "Was There a Gun?" Sports Illustrated, December 24, 1962
- Sailing Instructions, British Merchant Marine
- Light, John - Correspondence
- Translation of German Documents including Patrol Reports of U-20
- Xerox copies of originals sent by A. Worley (Box 9)
- Microfilm #198 - List of officers and passengers, statements of witnesses, U.S. Consul Frost, Mersey Inquiry, lives lost, cargo
- Letters from Canada's Department of National Defence on Canadian troops
- Yale University on Colonel House - Letters
- Cunard correspondence
- BBC broadcast
- Nicolas Tomalin of BBC, The Listener
- U.S. statutes on munition cargo in ships
- Letters to editors and book reviews
- Life magazine article by Simpson
- Correspondence regarding art work on the book
- Naval Ordnance correspondence and information (guns)
- International Law: information from American Journal of International Law on Lusitania
- Dollar awards to survivors
- U.S. Chief of Naval Operations Secret Dispatches on Unrestricted Submarine Warfare
- Beach, Captain E. L. - Correspondence
- Literary Digest excerpts
- Illustrations - Permissions to reprint
- Article by T. A. Bailey, "The Sinking of the Lusitania," American Historical Review,; "German Documents Relating to the Lusitania," Journal of Modern History, September 1936, October 1935
- List of journal and magazine titles regarding Lusitania
- O'Connor, Daniel (NBC) - Letters
- Article written for American Heritage (not published as of, June 1975)
- Light letters
- Bribery, etc. (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous British documents
- Cunard - H.M. Government agreement
- Mersey verdict (Original)
- Lusitania trip after turbine, 1913
- Mayer, Judge, obituary
- Orduna, S/S, 16 inch guns
- Stahl
- Mid-Channel issue and Zig-Zag
- British journal - Miscellaneous
- New York Times
  - May 1916-1965
  - November 1916
  - June 1915 -September 1915
  - May 1915
  - 1913-1915
- Mayer Trial and press
- Correspondence (T. A. Bailey), 1930's
- British Admiralty microfilm reels - List of contents
- 13 microfilm reels (Reel 1-13)
  Scope and Contents note
- 1 sound tape recording (Tape cabinet)